"Who Should Avoid Coffee?"
Despite the plethora
of health-promoting benefits
associated
with drinking coffee,
including a longer life,
could there be
any "grounds for concern?"
I've previously highlighted
how coffee is not for everyone.
People with glaucoma
or perhaps even merely
a family history
of the eye disease
may want to stay away
from caffeinated coffee,
as it can increase
pressure in the eye
and exacerbate
or contribute to glaucoma.
There are case reports
of individuals with epilepsy
having dramatic decreases
in the frequency of seizures
after stopping coffee,
so avoiding it
or limiting yourself
to no more than
two and half cups (590 ml)
is certainly worth a try
if you have a seizure disorder.
Coffee may also worsen
acid reflux disease.
U.S.
and European guidelines
for women
both suggest
reducing caffeine intake
to reduce symptoms
of urinary urgency
and frequency.
This makes sense.
Caffeine is a mild diuretic,
especially at doses found
in more than two or three cups
(480 or 720 ml) of coffee,
though daily consumers
may habituate
and be less impacted.
Surprisingly, though,
a meta-analysis
of observational studies
found no evidence of a link
between urinary incontinence
and coffee intake,
or caffeine, more generally.
In interventional studies
of caffeine reduction,
half found a decrease
in urinary frequency,
but for urinary incontinence,
only two studies out of seven
found a significant benefit.
Again, though, what's the harm
in giving it a try?
Caffeine intake
late in the day
can certainly disrupt
your sleep,
but the caffeine in four cups
(960 ml) of coffee
finished even six hours
before bedtime
can reduce total sleep time
by more than an hour,
and that was
in younger individuals.
Older adults' sleep
appears to be more sensitive
to caffeine.
The same 400 mg of caffeine,
which is less than what's in
a venti-sized coffee
from Starbucks,
cuts total sleep time
by about an hour
in young adults
(average age of 24),
but that same amount cuts off
more than two hours
among the middle-aged
(average age of 52).
What about just a single cup
(240 ml) of coffee at dinner?
It can indeed cause
a significant deterioration
in sleep quality.
There are also
consistent associations
between drinking coffee
and certain adverse outcomes
during pregnancy,
including miscarriage,
early preterm birth,
and low birth weight.
Although coffee consumption
has not been linked
to common birth defects,
it may increase the risk
of childhood leukemia.
For more on coffee
and pregnancy,
see my video
on how much is too much.
Also, don't stick it up
your butt.
A review on the questionable
safety of coffee enemas
warned against their use,
citing reports of colitis,
rectal burns, perforation,
and fatal
electrolyte disturbances.
Keep in mind
that daily consumption
of caffeinated beverages can
lead to physical dependence.
It's no coincidence
that Americans alone
spend more than $100 billion
annually on the stuff.
Caffeine withdrawal symptoms
can include days of headache,
fatigue,
difficulty concentrating,
and irritability.
Ironically, coffee's tendency
to become habit-forming
could turn out to be a perk
if coffee is indeed confirmed
to slow biological aging.